<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Hannah L Farrell</origin><origin>Seth M Munson</origin><pubdate>20221107</pubdate><title>RestoreNet subplot data for 21 sites within major dryland ecoregions throughout the southwestern United States, 2018 - 2021</title><geoform>tabular data</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Flagstaff, AZ</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><othercit>Additional information about Originators: Farrell, Hannah L, https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8740-8436; Munson, Seth M, https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2736-6374</othercit><onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9G7XRIK</onlink><lworkcit><citeinfo><origin>Hannah L Farrell</origin><origin>Seth M Munson</origin><origin>Bradley J Butterfield</origin><origin>Michael C Duniway</origin><origin>Akasha M Faist</origin><origin>Elise S Gornish</origin><origin>Caroline A Havrilla</origin><origin>Loralee Larios</origin><origin>Sasha C Reed</origin><origin>Helen I Rowe</origin><origin>Katherine M Laushman</origin><origin>Molly L McCormick</origin><pubdate>2022</pubdate><title>Soil surface treatments and precipitation timing determine seedling development across southwestern US restoration sites</title><geoform>journal manuscript</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Wiley Online Library</pubplace><publish>Ecological Applications</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://doi.org/XXXX</onlink></citeinfo></lworkcit></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>These data were compiled for a networked field-trial restoration experiment (RestoreNet) that spans the southwestern US, including 21 distributed field sites. The objective of our study was to understand the environmental factors and restoration practices (including seed mixes and soil manipulation) that increase plant establishment and survival to ultimate improve restoration outcomes in dryland environments. These data represent point-in-time plant density and height measurements at our field sites at the time of monitoring. These data were collected at 21 arid and semi-arid sites, located throughout Arizona, Utah, New Mexico, and California. These data were collected by USGS Restoration Assessment and Monitoring Program for the Southwest (RAMPS) within the Ecosystems Mission Area in collaboration with our partners. These data can be used to understand patterns of plant establishment and survival within the context of spatial and temporal environmental variation.</abstract><purpose>The purpose of these data are to provide information about plant responses to restoration treatments and seeding and environmental conditions at dryland sites in the southwestern US. These data were created to evaluate plant establishment, survival, and growth responses to environmental and and restoration variables; to compare plant responses across gradients of site characteristics and climate.</purpose><supplinf>These data provide height and density of seeded and naturally recruited species to emerge and survive over time at 21 restoration sites. Although each site manager was trained in our protocol, it was not always possible to identify species with a high degree of accuracy. Further, monitoring frequency varied widely across sites and ranged from monthly to twice annually, therefor tracking development of plants might not be possible in most instances. Data users should read the entire metadata record and review the 'Large Work Citation' to have a complete understanding of how these data were created and used. The data are specific to the uses identified in this metadata record and any other use of these data would be inappropriate. See 'Distribution liability' statements for more information.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>2018</begdate><enddate>2021</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><current>ground condition</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-118.309734</westbc><eastbc>-106.788656</eastbc><northbc>39.228361</northbc><southbc>31.58323</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt><themekey>atmospheric and climatic processes</themekey><themekey>biogeography</themekey><themekey>climate change</themekey><themekey>ecological processes</themekey><themekey>ecosystem monitoring</themekey><themekey>field inventory and monitoring</themekey><themekey>grassland ecosystems</themekey><themekey>plants (organisms)</themekey><themekey>precipitation (atmospheric)</themekey><themekey>remediation</themekey><themekey>soil resources</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>USGS information products</themekt><themekey>data release</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt><themekey>biota</themekey><themekey>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</themekey><themekey>environment</themekey><themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>arid</themekey><themekey>drylands</themekey><themekey>ecological modeling</themekey><themekey>ecological restoration</themekey><themekey>environmental conditions</themekey><themekey>environmental variables</themekey><themekey>field sites</themekey><themekey>growth responses</themekey><themekey>monitoring</themekey><themekey>plant density</themekey><themekey>plant establishment</themekey><themekey>plant growth</themekey><themekey>plant height</themekey><themekey>plant responses</themekey><themekey>plant survival</themekey><themekey>post-restoration</themekey><themekey>restoration experiment</themekey><themekey>restoration treatments</themekey><themekey>restoration seeding</themekey><themekey>restoration variables</themekey><themekey>seed mixes</themekey><themekey>seedling emergence</themekey><themekey>seedling survival</themekey><themekey>semi-arid</themekey><themekey>site characteristics</themekey><themekey>soil texture</themekey><themekey>spatial environmental variation</themekey><themekey>temporal change</themekey><themekey>temporal environmental variation</themekey><themekey>weedy species</themekey><themekey>zero-inflated data</themekey></theme><place><placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt><placekey>Arizona</placekey><placekey>Chihuahuan Desert</placekey><placekey>Colorado</placekey><placekey>Colorado Plateau</placekey><placekey>Mojave Desert</placekey><placekey>Sonoran Desert</placekey><placekey>California</placekey><placekey>New Mexico</placekey><placekey>Utah</placekey></place><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>southwestern US</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>none</accconst><useconst>none</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Seth M Munson</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>2255 North Gemini Drive</address><city>Flagstaff</city><state>AZ</state><postal>86001</postal><country>United States</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>928-556-7301</cntvoice><cntemail>smunson@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>Data collection was made possible through collaboration with Canyonlands Research Center, Tonto National Forest, McDowell Sonoran Conservancy, Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center, Antelope Valley Resource Conservation District, 29 Palms Inn, BLM Arizona/Utah/Colorado, Babbitt Ranches, Bar T Bar Ranch, Flying M Ranch, Tolani Lake Enterprises, Montezuma Well National Monument, Petrified Forest National Park, Jornada Experimental Range, Borderlands Restoration Network, Scottsdale Community College, Lake Pleasant Regional Park (Bureau of Reclamation and Maricopa County Parks), and Borderlands Restoration Network.</datacred></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic><complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>PRISM Climate Group at Oregon State University</origin><pubdate>20211029</pubdate><title>United States Average Total Precipitation, 1981-2010 (800m; BIL)</title><geoform>raster data</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Corvallis, OR, USA</pubplace><publish>PRISM Climate Group at Oregon State University</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://prism.oregonstate.edu/normals/</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>digital raster data</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19810101</begdate><enddate>20101231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>observed</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>Precipitation 30-Year Normals (annual values)</srccitea><srccontr>These climate data were used to populate the 'MAP' attribute field with data values based on the site coordinates (Latitude, Longitude). These data (1981-2010) are no longer available and have been replaced with 1991-2020 - 30-Year Normals.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>PRISM Climate Group at Oregon State University</origin><pubdate>20211026</pubdate><title>United States Average Daily Mean Temperature, 1981-2010 (800m; BIL)</title><geoform>raster data</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Corvallis, OR, USA</pubplace><publish>PRISM Climate Group at Oregon State University</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://prism.oregonstate.edu/normals/</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>digital raster data</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19810101</begdate><enddate>20201231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>observed</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>Mean temperature 30-Year Normals (annual values)</srccitea><srccontr>These climate data were used to populate the 'MAT' attribute field with data values based on the site coordinates (Latitude, Longitude).These data (1981-2010) are no longer available and have been replaced with 1991-2020 - 30-Year Normals.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>PRISM Climate Group at Oregon State University</origin><pubdate>20211026</pubdate><title>United States Daily Total Precipitation, Various dates from 7/11/2018 to 6/29/2021 (800m; BIL)</title><geoform>raster data</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Corvallis, OR, USA</pubplace><publish>PRISM Climate Group at Oregon State University</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://prism.oregonstate.edu/recent/</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>digital raster data</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19810101</begdate><enddate>20201231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>observed</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>Recent Years (Jan 1981 - Dec 2021)</srccitea><srccontr>These climate data were used to populate the 'Cumulative_Precip' and 'Precip_Since_Monitor' attribute fields with data values based on the site coordinates (Latitude_WGS84, Longitude_WGS84) and dates in the 'Date_Seeded' and 'Date_Monitored' attribute fields.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>US Environmental Protection Agency</origin><pubdate>20130416</pubdate><title>Level III Ecoregions of the Conterminous United States</title><geoform>ESRI shapefile</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Corvallis, OR</pubplace><publish>U.S. EPA Office of Research and Development (ORD) - National Health and Environmental Effects Research Laboratory (NHEERL)</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://www.epa.gov/eco-research/level-iii-and-iv-ecoregions-continental-united-states</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>digital vector data</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>20130101</begdate><enddate>20131231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>Publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>Level III Ecoregions</srccitea><srccontr>These ecoregion data were used to populate the 'Ecoregion_Level_3' attribute field with data values based on the site coordinates (Latitude_WGS84, Longitude_WGS84).</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Field data collection and recording, and development of the RestoreNet Subplots data table: Field data were collected by USGS technicians and partner institutions following a published protocol “Protocol for installing and monitoring a RestoreNet restoration field trial network site” (https://www.usgs.gov/publications/protocol-installing-and-monitoring-restorenet-restoration-field-trial-network-site ) using standardized datasheets developed for this project by USGS. Field observations (date monitored, plant density, height, and species functional group) were collected from 2018-2021  and entered into a master plant density datasheet, organized by site and treatment relevant info (Treatment, Plot) by a field manager as they were received. After cleaning the master datasheet (e.g. checking for continuity and spelling errors), relevant columns were copy/pasted into a new datasheet where other variable columns that were considered for our models were added based on the site and site dates. This final datasheet only includes data columns that were included in our final models. Develpment of the RestoreNet Subplots data table was completed using EXCEL and processing was completed in 2021.</procdesc><procdate>2021</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Data processing of PRISM data (precipitation and temperature): Using the 'Explorer' tool - Time Series Values for Individual Locations (https://prism.oregonstate.edu/explorer/), the spatial coordinates (Latitude_WGS84, Longitude_WGS84) for each site were used to acquire and analyze time-series data for a single location. Data values were acquired for both 30-year normals, 1981-2010 (monthly and annual) and daily values. Parameters for acquiring 30-year normals were set to Precipitation and Mean temp at 800m resolution and Units as SI (metric). For the daily values, data values were acquired for cumulative precipitation (Cumulative_Precip) and cumulative precipitation at the site from the previous monitoring period to the current monitoring period (Precip_Since_Monitor) with the parameters based on a start and end date of monitoring at the site. These data were downloaded as .csv tabular data, organized by site and date. The precipitation (MAP) and mean temperature (MAT) data values were entered into the appropriate cell in the RestoreNet_Subplots data table based on the 30-year normal for each site using EXCEL.</procdesc><procdate>2021</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Data processing of Level III Ecoregions data: The Level III Ecoregions shapefile (US Level III Ecoregions shapefile without state boundaries) was downloaded from the EPA Level III and IV Ecoregions of the Continental United States webpage (https://www.epa.gov/eco-research/level-iii-and-iv-ecoregions-continental-united-states). The shapefile files were extracted from the ZIP file, then the shapefile was added as a layer into ArcMap 10.8 (www.esri.com) for processing with the point location features (Sites). The 'Spatial Join' tool (Analysis Tools/Overlay Toolbox) was used to join attributes from the Level III Ecoregions features to the RestoreNet Subplots site point location based on the spatial relationship between the points and the polygon features. These features values were then exported from ArcMap to be included in the RestoreNet Subplots data table under the ‘Elevation_ft’ column for each site using EXCEL.</procdesc><procdate>2021</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Data processing of to acquire elevation data values: Elevation values were acquired using the location coordinates (lat and long) for each site by entering these spatial coordinate values into Google Earth Pro (Latitude_WGS84, Longitude_WGS84) and viewing the bottom of the screen which provides the latitude and longitude coordinates, elevation value (feet) and the Eye altitude, or the altitude that Google Earth is currently viewing the world from. The elevation values provided from Google Earth Pro were then entered into the appropriate cell (Elevation_ft column) for each site in the RestoreNet Subplots data table using EXCEL.</procdesc><procdate>2022</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Development of the RestoreNet Subplots data table: Data in this table represent: 1) variables related to the treatment type and timing (Date_Seeded, Treatment, Plot, Months_Since_Seeding,  Relative_Seed_Mix), 2) variables generated via field observations (Date_Monitored, Sand_Category, Clay_Category, Seeded_Sps_Fx_Grp, Densty, Height, Source), and 3) variables derived from spatial data sets based on the site coordinates and respective site installation and/or monitoring dates (Ecoregion_Level_3, MAP, MAT, Elevation_ft, Cumulative_Precip, Precip_Since_Monitor). Field observations (plant density, height, and species functional group) were collected by partners from 2018-2021 and entered into a master plant density datasheet, organized by site relevant info (Date_Seeded, Date_Monitored) and treatment relevant info (Treatment, Plot). After cleaning the master datasheet (e.g. checking for continuity and spelling errors), relevant columns were copy/pasted into a new datasheet where other variable columns that were considered for our models were added based on the site and site dates. This final datasheet only includes data columns that were included in our final models. Develpment of the RestoreNet Subplotsdata table was completed using EXCEL and processing was completed in 2021.</procdesc><procdate>2022</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Data Quality Assessment and Quality Control (QAQC): During data collection, we developed and utilized a set of protocols developed for the RestoreNet project to assure quality field data acquisition. All individuals who collected field data for this project were trained in appropriate field data collection and recording protocols. All collected data were reviewed by a project field manager who checked for consistency and quality in data content and formatting and entered all field data sheets into an electronic format from 2019-2021 using EXCEL. All data was then compiled into a single datasheet and checked for continuity by a single operator (lead author) in 2021 using EXCEL. All additional data (e.g., site environmental data extracted from online sources e.g., PRISM) was checked for data quality throughout a data entry process.</procdesc><procdate>2021</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Finalize Data for Dissemination: Data sent to the Southwest Biological Science Center Data Steward for dissemination and preservation per USGS Data Management Policies SM 502.6, SM 502.7, SM 502.8 and SM 502.9 (1 October 2016).</procdesc><procdate>2022</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>RestoreNet Subplots</enttypl><enttypd>This data table represents the plant height and density collected at 21 sites over 4 years of monitoirng (2018-2021). The purpose of this data table is to analyze plant responses to restoration treatments and environmental factors.</enttypd><enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>ID</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents a unique plant observation and data entry.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>13989</rdommax><attrunit>integer number</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Site</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the name of the restoration site.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>A textual description of the site and at the data collection point, to assist in identifying its location. Specific sites described by a code with cuppercase characters are listed below.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Latitude_WGS84</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the latitude coordinate for the site, WGS 1984.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>31.58323</rdommin><rdommax>39.228361</rdommax><attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Longitude_WGS84</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the longitude coordinate for the site, WGS 1984.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-118.309734</rdommin><rdommax>-112.122006</rdommax><attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Ecoregion_Level_3</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the EPA ecoregion (level 3) that the corresponding restoration site represents.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Arizona/New Mexico Mountains</edomv><edomvd>The Arizona/New Mexico Mountains are distinguished from neighboring mountainous ecoregions by their lower elevations and an associated vegetation indicative of drier, warmer environments, due in part to the region’s more southerly location. Forests of spruce, fir, and Douglas-fir, common in the Southern Rockies (21) and the Wasatch and Uinta Mountains (19), are only found in limited areas at the highest elevations in this region. Chaparral is common at lower elevations in some areas, pinyon-juniper and oak woodlands occur at lower and middle elevations, and the higher elevations are mostly covered with open to dense ponderosa pine forests. These mountains are the northern extent of some Mexican plant and animal species. Surrounded by deserts or grasslands, these mountains in Arizona and New Mexico can be considered biogeographical islands.</edomvd><edomvds>Environmental Protection Agency</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Arizona/New Mexico Plateau</edomv><edomvd>The Arizona/New Mexico Plateau represents a large transitional region between the drier shrublands and wooded higher relief tablelands of the Colorado Plateaus (20) in the north, the lower, hotter, less vegetated Mojave Basin and Range (14) in the west, and the semiarid grasslands of the Southwestern Tablelands (26) to the east. Higher, forest-covered mountainous ecoregions border the region on the northeast (21) and south (23). Local relief in the region varies from a few feet on plains and mesa tops to well over 1000 feet along tableland side slopes. The region extends across northern Arizona, northwestern New Mexico, and into the San Luis Valley of Colorado. Gunnison prairie dogs are a keystone species in many of the sagebrush ecosystems and their burrows provide habitat for other wildlife including burrowing owls, weasels, badgers, and a variety of snakes.</edomvd><edomvds>Environmental Protection Agency</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Chihuahuan Deserts</edomv><edomvd>This desert ecoregion extends from the Madrean Archipelago (79) in southeast Arizona to the Edwards Plateau (30) in south-central Texas. It is the northern portion of the southernmost desert in North America that extends more than 500 miles south into Mexico. It is generally a continuation of basin and range terrain that is typical of the Mojave Basin and Range (14) and Sonoran Basin and Range (81) ecoregions to the west, although the pattern of alternating mountains and valleys is not as pronounced. The mountain ranges are a geologic mix of Tertiary volcanic and intrusive granitic rocks, Paleozoic sedimentary layers, and some Precambrian granitic plutonic rocks. Outside the major river drainages, such as the Rio Grande and Pecos River in New Mexico and Texas, the landscape is largely internally drained. Vegetative cover is predominantly desert grassland and arid shrubland, except for high elevation islands of oak, juniper, and pinyon pine woodland. The extent of desert shrubland is increasing across lowlands and mountain foothills due to gradual desertification caused in part by historical grazing pressure.</edomvd><edomvds>Environmental Protection Agency</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Colorado Plateaus</edomv><edomvd>Ecoregion 20 is an uplifted, eroded, and deeply dissected tableland. Its benches, mesas, buttes, salt valleys, cliffs, and canyons are formed in and underlain by thick layers of sedimentary rock. Precipitous side-walls mark abrupt changes in local relief, often of 1000 to 2000 feet or more. The region contains a greater extent of pinyon-juniper and Gambel oak woodlands than the Wyoming Basin (18) to the north. There are also large low lying areas containing saltbrush-greasewood (typical of hotter, drier areas), which are generally not found in the higher Arizona/New Mexico Plateau (22) to the south where grasslands were typically more common. Summer moisture from thunderstorms supports warm season grasses not found in the Central Basin and Range (13) to the west. Many endemic plants occur and species diversity is greater than in Ecoregion 13. Several national parks are located in this ecoregion and attract many visitors to view their arches, spires, and canyons.</edomvd><edomvds>Environmental Protection Agency</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Madrean Archipelago</edomv><edomvd>Also known as the Sky Islands in the United States, this is a region of basins and ranges with medium to high local relief, typically 3000 to 5000 feet. Native vegetation in the region is mostly grama-tobosa shrubsteppe in the basins and oak-juniper woodlands on the ranges, except at higher elevations where ponderosa pine is predominant. The region has ecological significance as both a barrier and bridge between two major cordilleras of North America, the Rocky Mountains and the Sierra Madre Occidental. Its exceptional species richness and endemism are also influenced by both western desert and mid-continent prairie biogeography.</edomvd><edomvds>Environmental Protection Agency</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Mojave Basin and Range</edomv><edomvd>Stretching across southeastern California, southern Nevada, southwest Utah, and northwest Arizona, Ecoregion 14 is composed of broad basins and scattered mountains that are generally lower, warmer, and drier than those of the Central Basin and Range (13). Its creosotebush-dominated shrub community is distinct from the saltbush–greasewood and sagebrush–grass associations that occur to the north in the Central Basin and Range (13) and Northern Basin and Range (80); it is also differs from the palo verde–cactus shrub and saguaro cactus that occur in the Sonoran Basin and Range (81) to the south. In the Mojave, creosotebush, white bursage, Joshua-tree and other yuccas, and blackbrush are typical. On alkali flats, saltbush, saltgrass, alkali sacaton, and iodinebush are found. On mountains, sagebrush, juniper, and singleleaf pinyon occur. At high elevations, some ponderosa pine, white fir, limber pine, and bristlecone pine can be found. The basin soils are mostly Entisols and Aridisols that typically have a thermic temperature regime; they are warmer than those of Ecoregion 13 to the north. Heavy use of off-road vehicles and motorcycles in some areas has made the soils susceptible to wind and water erosion. Most of Ecoregion 14 is federally owned and grazing is constrained by the lack of water and forage for livestock.</edomvd><edomvds>Environmental Protection Agency</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Sonoran Basin and Range</edomv><edomvd>Similar in topography to the Mojave Basin and Range (14) to the north, this ecoregion contains scattered low mountains and has large tracts of federally owned lands, a large portion of which are used for military training. However, the Sonoran Basin and Range is slightly hotter than the Mojave and contains large areas of palo verde-cactus shrub and giant saguaro cactus, whereas the potential natural vegetation in the Mojave is largely creosote bush. Other typical Sonoran plants include white bursage, ocotillo, brittlebush, creosote bush, catclaw acacia, cholla, desert saltbush, pricklypear, ironwood, and mesquite. Winter rainfall decreases from west to east, while summer rainfall decreases from east to west. Aridisols and Entisols are dominant with hyperthermic soil temperatures and extremely aridic soil moisture regimes.</edomvd><edomvds>Environmental Protection Agency</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>MAP</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents mean annual precipitation for the site (PRISM; from 1981-2010; 800 m).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>97.61</rdommin><rdommax>534.93</rdommax><attrunit>millimeters</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>MAT</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents mean annual temperature at the site (PRISM; from 1981-2010; 800 m).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>8.5</rdommin><rdommax>22.4</rdommax><attrunit>degress Celsius</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Elevation_ft</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents elevation at the site.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1263</rdommin><rdommax>7486</rdommax><attrunit>feet</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Cumulative_Precip</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the total precipitation at the site from the time of seeding to the time of monitoring (PRISM; daily precipitation records; 800 m).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.54</rdommin><rdommax>1040.716001</rdommax><attrunit>millimeters</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Precip_Since_Monitor</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the total precipitation at the site from the previous monitoring period to the current monitoring period (PRISM; daily precipitation records; 800 m).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>448.489</rdommax><attrunit>millimeters</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Date_Seeded</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the date that the restoration site was seeded.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>7/11/2018</rdommin><rdommax>8/5/2020</rdommax><attrunit>date: mm/dd/yyyy</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Date_Monitored</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the date fo the corresponding monitoring.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>7/27/2018</rdommin><rdommax>6/29/2021</rdommax><attrunit>date: mm/dd/yyyy</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Treatment</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the restoration treatment that was applied at that plot.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>A.Control</edomv><edomvd>Plot received no seed or treatment</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>ConMod</edomv><edomvd>Plot received seed plus connectivity modifier (ConMod) treatment</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Mulch</edomv><edomvd>Plot received seed plus pine mulch treatment</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Pits</edomv><edomvd>Plots received seed plus pit (shallow 10 cm trough) treatment</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Seed Only</edomv><edomvd>Plot received seed only</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Sand_Category</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents how much sand is in the soil texture at the site (categorical).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>high</edomv><edomvd>The percent sand at a site were derived from 3 composite samples, randomly taken from 0 – 10 cm depth at each site; the soils were categorized into high categories of sand content according to the soil texture triangle (sand above 50% was considered “high”).</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>low</edomv><edomvd>The percent sand at a site were derived from 3 composite samples, randomly taken from 0 – 10 cm depth at each site; the soils were categorized into low categories of sand content according to the soil texture triangle (sand below 50% was considered “low”).</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Clay_Category</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents how much clay is in the soil texture at the site (categorical).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>high</edomv><edomvd>The percent clay at a site were derived from 3 composite samples, randomly taken from 0 – 10 cm depth at each site; the soils were categorized into high categories of clay content according to the soil texture triangle (clay above 25% was considered “high”).</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>low</edomv><edomvd>The percent clay at a site were derived from 3 composite samples, randomly taken from 0 – 10 cm depth at each site; the soils were categorized into low categories of clay content according to the soil texture triangle (clay below 25% was considered “low”).</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Relative_Seed_Mix</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents whether the seed mix applied in the corresponding plot was cool or warm, relative to each site.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Cool</edomv><edomvd>Classification assigned to the cooler-adatped of the two seed mixes seeded relative to the other seed mix seeded at the site based on temperature niche requirements (MAT50).</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Warm</edomv><edomvd>Classification assigned to the warmer-adatped of the two seed mixes seeded relative to the other seed mix seeded at the site based on temperature niche requirements (MAT50).</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>NA</edomv><edomvd>No seed mix was applied</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Plot</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the unique plot number within each site. Plot number is not unique across sites.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>44</rdommax><attrunit>integer number</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Seeded_Sps_Fx_Grp</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the plant functional group of the seeded species.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>annual forb</edomv><edomvd>Annual forb plant functional group</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>cool season grass</edomv><edomvd>Cool season grass (C3) plant functional group</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>NA</edomv><edomvd>not a seeded species</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>perennial forb</edomv><edomvd>Non-leguminous perennial forb plant functional group</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>perennial forb legume</edomv><edomvd>Leguminous perennial forb plant functional group</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>shrub</edomv><edomvd>Shrub plant functional group</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>unknown</edomv><edomvd>plant was known to be seeded, but unable to identify functional group with accuracy</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>warm season grass</edomv><edomvd>Warm season grass (C4) plant functional group</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Density</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the number of individual seedlings of each unique species in each 25 x 25 cm subplot. 0 represents no plants in the plot.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>400</rdommax><attrunit>integer number</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Height</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents the average height of each species within each subplot. 0 represents no plants in the plot. NA = unknown height; data collection or data entry error.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>1200</rdommax><attrunit>millimeters</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Source</attrlabl><attrdef>This attribute (column name) in the data table represents whether each plant species originated from the seed mix, was naturally recruited from the site, or was considered invasive.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Empty</edomv><edomvd>no plants in the plot</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Invasive</edomv><edomvd>a species identified by the local site manager to be weedy, noxious, or a species of concern</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Native_Recruited</edomv><edomvd>a species that was not seeded and is not weedy, originated from the site</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Seeded</edomv><edomvd>a species in the seed mix</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>NA</edomv><edomvd>not a seeded species</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr></detailed></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>GS ScienceBase</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal><country>United States</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>The author(s) of these data request that data users contact them regarding intended use and to assist with understanding limitations and interpretation. Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data for other purposes, nor on all computer systems, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab><techpreq>This file contains data available in comma-separated values (csv) format. The user must have software capable of displaying the datatable.</techpreq></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20221107</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Hannah L Farrell</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>2255 North Gemini Drive</address><city>Flagstaff</city><state>AZ</state><postal>86001</postal><country>United States</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>928-556-7301</cntvoice><cntemail>hfarrell@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>